<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A discourse of the soveraign power in a sermon preached at St. Mary Le Bow, Nov. 28, 1682, before the Artillery Company of London, and now published at their desire / by George Hickes ...</title>
            <author>Hickes, George, 1642-1715.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1682</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 59 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A43651</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H1845</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R2173</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12411517</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12411517</idno>
            <idno type="VID">61540</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A43651)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 61540)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 278:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A discourse of the soveraign power in a sermon preached at St. Mary Le Bow, Nov. 28, 1682, before the Artillery Company of London, and now published at their desire / by George Hickes ...</title>
                  <author>Hickes, George, 1642-1715.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 36 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Baker ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1682.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Divine right of kings --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Monarchy --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:61540:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:61540:1"/>
            <p>A DISCOURSE OF THE <hi>Souveraign Power,</hi> IN A SERMON PREACHED AT St. <hi>Mary Le Bow, Nov.</hi> 28. 1682.</p>
            <p>Before the <hi>Artillery Company</hi> OF LONDON.</p>
            <p>And now Publiſhed at their Deſire.</p>
            <p>By <hi>GEORGE HICKES,</hi> D.D. Chaplain in Ordinary to His MAJESTY.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>John Baker,</hi> Printer to the Honourable Society, at the <hi>Three Pigeons</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s <hi>Church-yard.</hi> 1682.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:61540:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:61540:2"/>
            <head>
               <list>
                  <item>To the Right Honourable Sir <hi>William Pritchard,</hi> Lord Mayor of the City of <hi>LONDON,</hi> And Preſident of the Artillery COMPANY.</item>
                  <item>To the Honourable, Sir <hi>James Smith,</hi> Knight and Alderman, Vice-Preſident.</item>
                  <item>To the Right Worſhipful, Sir <hi>Matthew Andrews,</hi> Treaſurer.</item>
               </list> As alſo to the Right Honourable,
<list>
                  <item>Duke of <hi>Albermarle,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Earl of <hi>Oxford,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Earl of <hi>Arundel,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Lord <hi>Falkland,</hi>
                  </item>
               </list> To the Honourable, and Right Worſhipful,
<list>
                  <head>STEWARDS.</head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Henry Guy,</hi> 
                     <abbr>Eſq</abbr>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>William Legg,</hi> 
                     <abbr>Eſq</abbr>
                  </item>
                  <item>Sir <hi>William Dodſon,</hi> Kt.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Charles Duncomb,</hi> 
                     <abbr>Eſq</abbr>
                  </item>
               </list> And to the whole Court of Aſſiſtants, Field-Officers, Captains, and Gentlemen, Profeſſing and Exerciſing Arms in that Renowned and Honourable Society.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honourable,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IN Obedience to your Deſire, I have Publiſhed this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, which I Preached before you on your late Anni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary Solemnity; and if it may contribute to the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Satisfaction of any who are already Loyal, or the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction, and Reformation of ſuch as are not truly ſo, I ſhall be thankful to God for Bleſſing ſo mean a Performance with ſuch happy ſucceſs. The Subject, I am ſure, is ſuitable to the
<pb facs="tcp:61540:3"/>Occaſion upon which it was Preach'd, and very neceſſary for the Times; but yet I fore-ſee it will diſpleaſe ſome Men, whoſe Diſpleaſure indeed I do not value, becauſe their Favour is not to be obtained by any Miniſter of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> who will not be falſe to his own Profeſſion, and utterly decline the Preaching upon theſe Doctrines, and Duties, which I have here plainly Taught. But you have not ſo Learned Chriſt, as appears by the Entertainment, which this unpoliſhed Sermon hath found among you, meerly for the Truths ſake. Your Approbation will be Protection ſufficient both to it and the Author, who Preſents it unto you with all due Obſervance, wiſhing a daily increaſe of ſuch Obedient and Dutiful Subjects to His Majeſty, as you are, to whoſe firm and active Loyalty, next unto God's and our Governours Vigilant Care and Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, we owe our preſent Order, and Peace. I am,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Right Honourable,</salute> 
               <signed>Your moſt Obedient Servant, <hi>George Hickes.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:61540:3"/>
            <head>A SERMON Preached before The Artillery Company.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>Rom. 13.4.</bibl>
               <q>He beareth not the Sword in Vain: for he is the Miniſter of God.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>The context before, and after is this: <hi>Wilt thou then not be afraid of the Power? do that which is good, and thou ſhalt have praiſe of the ſame. For he is the Miniſter of God, to thee for good: But if thou do that which is evil, be afraid, for he beareth not the Sword in Vain, for he is the Miniſter of God, a Revenger to Execute wrath upon him, that doth evil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Ltho there now are, and have been for above Two thouſand years, many Forms of Civil Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment in the World, yet all Hiſtorians Scared, or Civil, that write of the times near unto the Flood, aſſure us, that Monarchies were every where erected
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:61540:4"/>in thoſe Ages, and that Kings were then the Soveraigns of the Earth. Popular Governments, whether by the whole body of the People, as in <hi>Democracies;</hi> or in a Select number of the Chief, as in <hi>Ariſtocracies,</hi> were then in the Wombs of their ſpecial cauſes, being afterwards introduced either by the compact and agreement of Men, free to chooſe their own Government, as in new Colonies, and Diſperſions; or elſe by Rebellion, as in the famous Commonwealth of <hi>Rome,</hi> which at firſt was Governed by<note n="†" place="margin">Urbem Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mam à princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pio reges habuere, <hi>Tacit.</hi>
               </note> Kings after the moſt Primitive Form, and then after the Rebellion of <hi>Brutus, Valerius</hi> and <hi>Collatinus</hi> by the<note n="★" place="margin">S. P. Q. R.</note> four great Letters, <hi>the Senat, and People of Rome,</hi> and at laſt again by Kings; upon whom firſt under the name of<note n="★" place="margin">Nomine principis ſub imperium ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepit, <hi>Tacit.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Prince,</hi> and then under the Titles of <hi>Emperor,</hi> and <hi>Auguſtus, the Senat, and People,</hi> not able to ſecure the publick Peace without a Soveraign Head, conferred all their Power; and as the Greek, and Latin Hiſtorians, obſerve, really made them <hi>Kings,</hi> altho, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent offence on both ſides, they muſt not <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſooth</hi> be ſo called.</p>
            <p>It was under <hi>Claudius</hi> the 5th. or <hi>Nero</hi> the Sixth of theſe Emperours, that St. <hi>Paul</hi> wrote this Epiſtle unto the <hi>Romans,</hi> in which it is to be obſerved, that he aſſerts the <hi>Roman</hi> Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror to be the Miniſter of God, altho he was choſen by the Army, or the People, or ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times by both, for even in Elective Monarchies,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:61540:4"/>where the People chooſe the <hi>Soveraign,</hi> he hath not his Authority from his Electors, but from God, as in Oeconomical Government, the Prince of the Family, if I may ſo ſpeak, hath not his Autority as an Husband, from the Wife, who choſe him for her Husband, nor the Autority of a Maſter, from the Servant who choſe him for his Maſter, But his Conjugal, and Deſpotical Autority are both from God, who hath made the Husband the head of his Wife, <hi>as Chriſt is the head of the Church,</hi> and the Maſter Lord, and Commander over his Servants, <hi>whom they are to count worthy of all Honour, and be Obedient unto them, as unto Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The choice indeed of the Husband, and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter is from the Wife, and Servant, but the Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of them both is from God, they were free, as to their choice, but aſter it they are not free, as to their ſubjection, nor can they diſobey them without diſobeying God. Juſt ſo is it in E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lective Monarchies, the People or their Deputies may chooſe the Man whom they will have for their <hi>Prince,</hi> but they do not give him his Auto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity; <hi>that</hi> he hath from God upon their Election, which made <hi>Valentinian</hi> when the Army, that choſe him Emperor, cry'd out, that he ſhould take a partner in the Government, anſwer them upon this principle thus:<note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>Sozom.</hi> L. 6. C. 6.</note> 
               <hi>It was in your Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er</hi> Souldiers, <hi>to chooſe me for your Emperor, but now you have choſen me, that which you demand is not in your Power, but mine: you ought to be
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:61540:5"/>quiet, as Subjects, and I as an Emperor to conſider, what is fit to be done.</hi> And accordingly the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle here in my text aſſerts <hi>Claudius,</hi> or as it is more likely, <hi>Nero</hi> the Emperor, who was cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen by the Army, and <hi>Senat,</hi> not to be <hi>their</hi> Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter, or to have any Miniſterial, or Fiduciary Power <hi>under</hi> them, but to be the Miniſter of God <hi>over</hi> them, and <hi>as ſuch</hi> to have the Power of the Sword. <hi>He beareth not the Sword in Vain, for he is the Miniſter of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>According to which explication of the words, I ſhall undertake to prove two propoſitions. Firſt, <hi>That Soveraign Princes are Gods Miniſters, and Vice-Gerents, and Reign by his ſpecial ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance and appointment.</hi> and Secondly, <hi>That as ſuch they have and exerciſe the Supream Power, and particularly the Power of the Sword.</hi> And theſe two Propoſitions being proved, I ſhall make ſome practical inferences from this Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Doctrin, proper to <hi>this Audience</hi> and the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence of the Times, in which we live.</p>
            <p>I. Firſt then, that Soveraign Princes are Gods Miniſters, and Vice-Gerents, and Reign by his ſpecial ordinance, is plain from many expreſs texts of the Old and New Teſtament, which are the Loyalleſt, as well as the Divineſt Books in the World. I will begin with the Old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, whoſe Autority, were it not of divine inſpiration, ought upon the account of its an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity, to preponderate with us above any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Volume in the World.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:61540:5"/>
            <p> There, as<note n="†" place="margin">l. 5. c. 24.</note> 
               <hi>Irenaeus</hi> obſerves, God ſaith in the 8th. Ch. of the Book of <hi>Poverbs, By me Kings Reign, and Princes decree juſtice, by me Princes rule, and Nobles, even all the Judges of the Earth.</hi> Hence <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> King of <hi>Babylon</hi> is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Gods Servant, or Miniſter, <hi>Jerem.</hi> 27.5, 6. <hi>I have made the Earth, and given it unto whom it ſeemed meet unto me, and now I have given all theſe Lands into the hands of</hi> Nebuchadnezzar <hi>the King of</hi> Babylon <hi>my Servant, and all Nations ſhall ſerve him, and his Son, and his Sons Son, untill the very time of his Land come, and then many Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and great Kings ſhall ſerve themſelves of him.</hi> Accordingly when <hi>Daniel</hi> ſpoke unto him, he ſaid, <hi>Thou O King art a King of Kings, for the God of Heaven, hath given thee a Kingdom, Power, and Strength, and Glory.</hi> Chap. 2.37. and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards ſpeaking of him unto <hi>Belſhazzar</hi> his Son, he ſaid. <hi>O thou King! the moſt high God gave</hi> Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buchadnezzar <hi>thy Father a Kingdom, and Majeſty,</hi> and Glory, and Honor, and for the Majeſty, that <hi>he gave him, all People trembled, and feared before him; whom he would he ſlew, and whom he would he kept alive, and whom he would he ſet up, and whom he would he pulled down.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>According to this Doctrine alſo God calleth <hi>Cyrus</hi> his <hi>Shepherd,</hi> and <hi>Anointed;</hi> the very Titles, which he gave the Kings of Iſrael, whom he ſet over his own People. <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord, I am the Lord that maketh all things, that
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:61540:6"/>Stretcheth forth the Heavens alone, that ſaith of</hi> Cyrus <hi>he is my Shepherd;</hi> and, <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord to</hi> Cyrus <hi>his Anointed, I have even called thee by thy name, I have ſurnamed thee, tho thou haſt not known me.</hi> I have choſen to inſtance in theſe two Pagan Kings, rather than in the Kings of Iſrael, becauſe you may ſee, that there is no difference among Soveraign Princes, as to the Divinity of their Title, but that the Sacred Order of Kings in general, is the Ordinance of God. And therefore God to Lecture this Doctrine more Emphatically unto us, hath together with the Soveraign Autority communicated unto them his own name. <hi>Thou ſhalt not revile the Gods</hi> (ſaith God) <hi>nor curſe the ruler of thy People,</hi> and ſaith the Pſalmiſt, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 82. <hi>God ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth in the Congregation of the Mighty, he Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth among the Gods; and I have ſaid ye are Gods, and all of you are Children of the moſt high.</hi> In alluſion to which (ſaith our Saviour) in his own defence, <hi>Is it not written in your Law, I ſaid ye are Gods: and if he called them Gods about whom the word of God was ſpoken, ſay ye of him, whom the Father hath ſanctified, and ſent into the World, thou blaſphemeſt, becauſe thou ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt I am the Son of God.</hi> That is as much as to ſay, if Kings, who arc <hi>Anointed and ſent by God</hi> are called Gods, and the Sons of God, then how can it be blaſphemy in me, who am the Meſſias himſelf ſent from God, to ſay I am his Son.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:61540:6"/>
            <p> Yes, Kings are petty Gods, who Govern men upon Earth as <hi>Michael</hi> and <hi>Gabriel</hi> Govern their Angels in Heaven, by immediate dele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation from God. Their Soveraignty is an Image of his Soveraignty, their Majeſty the Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure of his Majeſty, and their Empire a ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militude of his Empire, they are Supream on Earth, as he is in Heaven, they derive not their Autority from their Subjects (for that would be a contradiction) as he derives not his from his creatures, but from him alone they derive it, they are his Lieutenants, and Truſtees, the honor or diſhonor we do them terminates in him, who gives them their Scep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and ſets them as the Scripture ſaith, he ſet <hi>Solomon</hi> upon his own Throne, and made him King, for the Lord his God. 1 <hi>Chr.</hi> 29.23.2 <hi>Chr.</hi> 9.8.</p>
            <p>This is further evident out of the New Teſtament, from that ſolemn acknowledgment which our bleſſed Saviour as a Subject of the Empire, made of the Soveraign Power of <hi>Tiberius,</hi> whom he owned, by paying the Tribute, which was due unto him, for the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter of God. <hi>For, for this cauſe</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>pay you Tribute alſo, becauſe they are Gods Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, attending continually upon this very thing.</hi> To which I ſhall only add the verſes before, and after my text: <hi>Let every ſoul be ſubject to the higher pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, for there is no power but of God, the powers that be
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:61540:7"/>are ordained of God, whoſoever therefore reſiſteth the power reſiſteth the ordinance of God, and they that reſiſt ſhall receive to themſelves damnation.—Wilt thou then not be afraid of the Power, do that which is good and thou ſhalt have praiſe of the ſame, for he is the Miniſter of God to thee for good. But if thou do that, which is evil, be afraid, for he beareth not the Sword in Vain; for he is the Miniſter of God, a revenger to execute wrath up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him, that doth evil. Wherefore, you ought to be ſubject not only for wrath, but alſo for Conſcience ſake.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here you ſee how Emphatically the Apoſtle ſtyleth the Power, <hi>the Ordinance,</hi> and the Poten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate, or Ruler, <hi>the Miniſter</hi> of God. And accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to this Apoſtolical leſſon the Primitive Chriſtians did acknowledge the Autority of their perſecuting Emperors to be derived from God.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="†" place="margin">Ad Antol. <hi>L. 1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Theophilus</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Antioch</hi> ſaith, <hi>I will honor the Emperor, but not adore him, I dore the true God, knowing, that by him the Emperor is ordain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</hi> And to the ſame purpoſe again, <hi>He is not himſelf God, but a man appointed by God, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a ſort entruſted by God, with the Oeconomy of the Empire.</hi> So<note n="*" place="margin">Legat. pro Chriſt.</note> 
               <hi>Athenagoras</hi> Addreſſing his ſpeech to <hi>Marcus Antoninus,</hi> and his Son <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modus: to you</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>the power of all things is committed, you have received the Empire from above. So</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">L. 8.</note> Origen <hi>tells</hi> Celſus, <hi>that it was not the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:61540:7"/>Heathen God</hi> Saturn, <hi>but God who Governeth all things, that ſetteth up Kings, and giveth them Power to Reign,</hi> and<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccleſ. Hiſt.</hi> l. 7. c. 11.</note> in <hi>Euſebius, Dionyſius</hi> of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexandria</hi> ſaith in the name of the Chriſtians, <hi>we worſhip, and adore the one God, who hath committed the Kingdom to out Sacred Emperors</hi> Valcrianus, <hi>and</hi> Gallienus? And<note n="*" place="margin">l. 5. c. 24.</note> 
               <hi>Prenoeus</hi> Biſhops, and Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr, after a particular proof of this Doctrine by many texts of Scripture, and this of mine among the reſt, concludes with theſe words: <hi>By whoſe Command Kings are born Men, by his Command likewiſe are Men ordained Kings.</hi> And ſo <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullian</hi> after him: <hi>Thence is the Emperor from whence he was a man, before he was Emperor, thence he hath this Autority, from whence he hath his breath</hi> And again. <hi>We muſt of neceſſity reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence the Emperor, as one, that our Lord hath choſen, ſo that we may reaſonably ſay, that</hi> Caeſar <hi>is rather ours, than yours, as being ordained by our God.</hi> Apol. c. 30.33. and in another place, <hi>a Chriſtian is an Enemy to no man, much leſs to the Emperor, whom he knows to be appointed by God,</hi> ad Scapul.</p>
            <p>This was current Divinity among the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans under the Pagan and Perſecuting Emperors, and what it was after they turned Chriſtians, may be ſeen in the Apology of St. <hi>Athanaſrus,</hi> unto <hi>Conſtanius,</hi> eſpecially from theſe words: <hi>O Almighty Lord, eternal King, the Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, thou by thy word haſt given the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:61540:8"/>Empire to thy ſervant</hi> Conſtantius. It would be endleſs to cite more Autorities to confirm this Doctrine out of the Fathers, I will rather ſhew how it hath been taught by our own Acts, and Authors, of our own Soveraigns, the Kings of the <hi>Engliſh</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Sir <hi>Orland. Bridgmans</hi> ſpeech to the Regicides p. 12, 13, 14.</note> Empire, to whom God hath given this<note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>Granmers</hi> Letters to Qu. <hi>Mary.</hi>
               </note> Imperial Crown, the Statute of Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munire <hi>lb.</hi> K. 2. c. 5. declares, that <hi>the Crown of</hi> England <hi>is ſo free that it is in no Earthly Subjecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but immediately ſubject to God in all things touching the regality of the ſame.</hi> And the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament in the 25 <hi>H.</hi> 8.21. made this recogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion unto his Majeſty, that <hi>his Graced Realm had no Superiour under God, but only his Grace.</hi> and (24 <hi>H.</hi> 8. c. 12.) <hi>and that next unto God they ought him a Natural, and Humble Obedience:</hi> And long before this our Ancient, and learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Lawyer <hi>Bracton</hi> did declare, that <hi>the</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">L. 1 <hi>de rer. diviſ.</hi> c. 2.</note> 
               <hi>King is the Vicar, and Miniſter of God, and Chriſt, that he</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">L. 2. c. 22.</note> 
               <hi>hath neither equal, nor Superiour, and that</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">L. 1. <hi>de ver. diviſ.</hi> c. 8.</note> 
               <hi>every Soul is under him, but he is under none ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept only God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for Eccleſiaſtical Autorities it would take up too much time to recite them all. The<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Canon</hi> 36. <hi>Art.</hi> 1.</note> Church is to admit none into holy orders, but ſuch as will firſt ſubſcribe, that <hi>the Kings Majeſty next under God, is the only Supream Governor of all his Realsm and Dominions,</hi> and in the Book of<note n="†" place="margin">ſee hom. about obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence part 1. and againſt wilful Rebell. p. 1.</note> 
               <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies</hi> beſides the aſſertion of this Doctrine a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:61540:8"/>Soveraign Princes in general, our late Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign King <hi>James</hi> is acknowledged for the <hi>high gift of God.</hi> To conclude this head, from hence it comes to paſs, that our Kings, as the learned<note n="*" place="margin">In Epiſtolâ ad virun. Ampl. D. Morley.</note> 
               <hi>Bochart</hi> obſerved, are ſtiled <hi>by the Grace of God,</hi> and that the Royal Motto is <hi>Dieu et mon Droit;</hi> and accordingly this Church which is ſo Pure, and Primitive in her Loyalty hath taught her Children to Pray: <hi>Almighty God whoſe King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom is everlaſting, and Power infinite, have mercy upon the whole Church, and ſo rule the heart of thy</hi> Choſen Servant <hi>Charles, our King and Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, that he knowing,</hi> whoſe Miniſter he is, <hi>may above all things ſeek thy Honour, and Glory, and that we, and all his Subjects duly conſidering</hi> whoſe Autority he hath, <hi>may faithfully ſerve, honor, and humbly obey him,</hi> in thee, and for thee, <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to thy bleſſed Word, and Ordinance.</hi> Yes, according to the word of the Apoſtle in my text, who ſaith, that <hi>the beareth not te Sword in Vain, becauſe he is the Miniſter of God</hi>
            </p>
            <p>II. Having now ſhewed, that <hi>Soveraign Princes are Gods Miniſters, and Vice-Gerents; and Reign by his ſpecial appointment,</hi> I proceed to ſhew in the ſecond place, that <hi>under that Character they have and exerciſe the Supream Power, and particularly the Power of the Sword.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This latter Propoſition is a very eaſy and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernable conſequence from the former, and may
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:61540:9"/>be illuſtrated from the nature of ſubordinate Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates who are the Kings Miniſters, appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed under him, as he is appointed under God. As for example: the Lord Lieutenant of <hi>Ireland</hi> is the Kings Miniſter, and Vice-Gerent, and by conſequence under that character he hath, and exerciſes the Supream Power in the Government of that Kingdom both Civil, and Military, both that of the Scepter, and that of the Sword, which the King hath committed unto him.</p>
            <p>In like manner Soveraign Princes being, as I have ſhewn, Gods <hi>Lieutenants,</hi> and <hi>Vice-Gerents</hi> within their ſeveral Realms, and Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, they Reign under that Sublime character, and as his Repreſentiatives have, and exerciſe all Juriſdiction, and in particular that of the Sword; accordingly, as the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>he beareth not the Sword in Vain, for he is the Miniſter of God, a revenger to execute wrath, or puniſhment, upon him, that doth evil.</hi> Were men of the temper of the Angels, who obey their Superiours pure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for Conſcience-ſake, then it would be ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent for Princes, that they had the commanding without the Puniſhing Power, but ſince moſt men are ſubject more for Fear, than Conſcience, it is highly neceſſary, that the Soveraign ſhould be furniſhed with the Coercive, and Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicative Power, which may be called <hi>the Sword of Juſtice,</hi> and without which all his Laws, and
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:61540:9"/>Orders would be vain, precarious and inſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficant words, and writings, meer Cobwebs, which the Waſps and Hornets, that ſwarm in all Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernments, would inſultingly break through.</p>
            <p>And were men alſo like the good Angels free from evil paſſions, would they be quiet in the ſeveral ranks and ſtations, in which God hath ſet them, then Soveraign Princes like Arch-Angels, who are ſecure from the inſurrections of their Subjects, would be ſafe without the Sword; but ſince <hi>Pride, Envy,</hi> and <hi>Diſcontent,</hi> make men envy their Superiours, and ſtrive to ſnatch the Crowns from off their Princes heads, ſince there are <hi>Lucifers</hi> in all Kingdoms, and the Dragon, and his Angels will in all worldly Governments, be ſtill fighting with <hi>Michael,</hi> and his; it is ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely neceſſary, that the <hi>Soveraign</hi> be furniſhed with the Supream Command, Government, and Diſpoſition of the Militia, or Military Forces, which may be called the <hi>Sword of War.</hi> Further<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more it is neceſſary for the Soveraign to bear the Sword of War, not only to defend himſelf from his own Rebellious Subjects, but to defend both himſelf, &amp; his people from the invaſions of other Soveraigns; for it is not upon Earth, as it is in Heaven, where one Principality can live without danger, or jealouſie of anothe but in all Earthly Kingdoms there muſt be military Societies, &amp; Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parations ready to oppoſe foreign violence, actual
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:61540:10"/>and Potential Forces, ſome every where, as the Hiſtorian ſpeaks, <hi>in equis &amp; Armis ad ſubita belli excubantes,</hi> and if this Power of levying War, and providing Arms, and Forces, did belong to any other perſon, than him whom God hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for Soveraign, that perſon would be So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign, and not he.</p>
            <p>From whence it is plain, that the Prince hath the Sword in both ſenſes, from the ſame hand, from which he hath his Robes, his Crown, and his Scepter. He is a Soveraign as Gods Vice-Gerent and Repreſentative, and as Gods Vice-Gerent and Repreſentative he is a Soveraign, and under both, or either character he holds the Sword, by the Autority of his Heavenly Maſter; who hath put it in his hand for his Peoples defence and alſo to be an avenger, to execute wrath upon every ſoul that is diſobedient to the Laws, which are made to defend his rights, againſt the inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of his Subjects, or he rights of his Subjects, againſt the violence, and invaſions of one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. In both theſe reſpects he is an Avenger, and God to whom Vengeance, and the Power of life, and death over men Radically, and Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally belongeth, hath committed the Sword of War, and Juſtice unto him, that he might be <hi>Vindex in terris,</hi> and not only Command, but Puniſh in his ſtead.</p>
            <p>Hence the Emperor <hi>Juſtinian,</hi> who accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:61540:10"/>to my firſt propoſition, in the firſt ſentence of his Preface to the Pandects ſolemnly<note n="*" place="margin">Deo Autore noſtrum, guber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nante imperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um, quod no-bis à coeleſti Majeſtate tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditum eſt, prae fat I. digeſt.</note> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledges, that <hi>he received his Empire from God,</hi> doth in the beginning of his Proem to the Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions aſſert <hi>Arms to be primarily neceſſary for a Prince,</hi> in the following words: <hi>Imperatoriam Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtatem non ſolum Armis decoratam, ſed etiam le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gibus oportet eſſe armatam.</hi> The Majeſty of a King ought to be fortified and adorned not only with Arms, but Laws. With Arms in the firſt place, without which his Majeſty would be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible and his Laws of no force; for take away the Teeth, and Talons of the Lyon, and his Roaring, to which <hi>Solomon</hi> ingeniouſly compares the wrath of a King, ſhall be no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger terrible, but every vile Dog will bark, and every ſilly Aſs will bray in his face, and lift up his heels againſt him.</p>
            <p>Hence ſaith<note n="*" place="margin">Prolog. tract. de leg. &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuet. regn. Angl.</note> 
               <hi>Glanvil</hi> of the Kings of <hi>England</hi> almoſt in the words of <hi>Juſtinian, Regiam Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtatem non ſolum armis oportet eſſe decoratam, ſed &amp; legibus;</hi> and to this purpoſe<note n="†" place="margin">L. 1. c. 27.</note> 
               <hi>Fleta, habet Rex in manu ſuâ omnia jura,</hi> the King hath all the Laws in his hand, <hi>&amp; materialem gladium, qui per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinet, ad Regni gubernaculum,</hi> and the Sword, which belongeth to the Government of his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and ſaith <hi>Bracton</hi> in the beginning of his firſt Book; <hi>In rege, qui reclè regit, neceſſaria ſunt duo baec, arma videlicet, &amp; leges,</hi> there are two things neceſſary for a King, that Governs well,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:61540:11"/>Arms, and Laws. Hence the Laws of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, which acknowledg the imperial Crown, and Juriſdiction of his Realm, to be taken im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately from God, according to my firſt Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, do alſo according to the ſecond, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledg <hi>the Kings Power over the Militia, and that force of Armour belongs unto him, by vertue of his Royal Seignory,</hi> as may be ſeen in the 7 of <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> I. and in the 13 of our preſent Soveraign, c. 6. where it is declared, that <hi>the ſupream diſpoſition of the Militia, and of all Forces by Sea, and Land, and of all Forts, and places of ſtrength is, and by the Laws of</hi> England <hi>ever was the right of His Majeſty, and his Royal Predeceſſors.</hi> And if it were not, he would not be a real, but a meer nominal King, in ſhew a Soveraign, or ſhadow of a Soveraign, but in reality a Subject, a <hi>Spar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan</hi> King, a <hi>diſtreſſed Prince</hi> indeed, not Gods, but the Peoples unhappy Miniſter and Servant; which his Majeſty, of his great wiſdom, knew very well, when he told that Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, which asked the Militia of him for ſome weeks, that <hi>he would not part with it for an hour.</hi> It was the voice of a King, and a Chriſtian, he ſpoke as it became Gods Vice-Gerent, and Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant, who knew very well from whom he had his Sword as well as his Scepter, and that he bore it not in vain, but was the Miniſter of God, a Revenger to execute wrath upon him, or <hi>them,</hi> that do evil.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:61540:11"/>
            <p> Having now ſhewed firſt that ſovereign Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces are God's miniſters and vicegerents; and ſecondly, that as ſuch, they have, and exerciſe the ſupreme power, and particularly that of the Sword; I now proceed to make ſome practical Obſervations upon this Loyal doctrine proper to this meeting, and the exigence of theſe times<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> in which we live.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt</hi> then, we may obſerve what a groundleſs and blaſphemous doctrine it is to aſſert, as the Popiſh Writers do, that the <hi>Pope</hi> hath all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of temporal, as well as ſpiritual power gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven him from God, and that he giveth the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer to Emperours and Kings to uſe it under him; but ſo, that as his miniſters and vicege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, they depend entirely upon him.</p>
            <p>This is the great <hi>Palladium</hi> of the Popiſh Cauſe, which hath murthered, and depoſed ſo many ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereign Princes, and diſpoſed of their Crowns and Dominions. This brought <hi>Henry</hi> the IV. Emperour of <hi>Germany,</hi> on a cold froſty day, bare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foot and bare headed to Pope <hi>Hildebrand</hi>'s pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace; this brought the Emperour <hi>Frederick</hi> the firſt, to hold Pope <hi>Adrian</hi> the 4th's Stirrop; and this ſet the foot of Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> the 3d upon his Neck, when his Holineſs blaſphemouſly miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>applyed the words of the <hi>Pſalmiſt: Thou ſhalt tread upon the Lion and Adder, the young Lion and Dragon, thou ſhalt trample under foot.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:61540:12"/>
            <p> It was upon this account of the Pope's pretended univerſal Sovereignty that King <hi>John</hi> ſurrendred this Kingdom to Pope <hi>Innocent</hi> the 3d that <hi>Henry</hi> the 2d ſubmitted to the laſhes of the Monks of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> and that <hi>Henry</hi> the 4th. of <hi>France,</hi> was whipped in the Perſon of his Ambaſſadour Cardinal <hi>D'oſſat,</hi> by the Pope and Cardinals at <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To be ſhort, this doctrine makes all Princes the Pope's Vaſſals, and it ought not to be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dured by any Loyal Chriſtian Subject, as being ſo unreaſonable in it ſelf, ſo deſtructive to the rights and dignity of ſovereign Princes, and ſo contrary to the word of God. Our Anceſtours themſelves were never able to bear it, as <note n="*" place="margin">Colces <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtit. part</hi> 4. p. 13, 14.</note> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears from the reſolve of the Lords and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons in Parliament, in the 40 year of <hi>Edward</hi> the 3d who when the Pope by his Ambaſſadour demanded Homage of the King for his two Kingdoms, anſwered, that <hi>King</hi> John (upon whoſe ſurrender the Pope grounded his claim) <hi>could not put his Realm in any ſuch ſubjection without his peoples conſent, that it was againſt his Coronation Oath, and that for themſelves they could not aſſent to any thing in Parliament, that tended to the diſinberiſon of the King and his Crown, and that if the Pope at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted any thing of that nature, they would reſiſt him with all their force.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And in the Stature of <hi>Praemunire,</hi> wherein as I have ſhew'd, the three Eſtates of this Realm
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:61540:12"/>acknowledged the King to be immediately ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to God, they alſo promiſed and bound themſelves to defend the King's Crown and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gality againſt the Papal Juriſdiction, and to live and dye with the ſame.</p>
            <p>And in the 35 <hi>Hen.</hi> VIII. 11. the firſt oath of Supremacy, which acknowledges the King ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Head upon earth under God, was alſo formed againſt the Papal Juriſdiction; which made Arch-Biſhop <hi>Cranmer,</hi> in Queen <hi>Mary</hi>'s days, refuſe to anſwer the Biſhop of <hi>Gloceſter,</hi> who ſate in judgment upon him by commiſſion from <hi>Rome;</hi> for which refuſal he apologized in a Letter to the Queen, urging his Oath of Allegiance to the contrary, and telling her Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, <hi>that it could not but grieve the heart of any natural Subject to be accuſed,</hi> as he was, <hi>of his own Sovereign within her own Realm, before an outward Judge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But in the <hi>ſecond</hi> place, we may obſerve what an abſurd doctrine it is, and how diſagreeable to Chriſtian divinity, to aſſert that the ſovereign Power is radically and originally ſeated in the People, and derived from them upon the Prince. I deny not, but that God by his providence may inveſt the ſovereign Power in the body of the people, as ſormerly in <hi>Athens,</hi> and now in the Cantons of <hi>Switzerland,</hi> and that, as formerly in <hi>Sparta,</hi> they may commit the exerciſe of it unto a ſingle perſon under the character of King; but
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:61540:13"/>then ſuch Kings are on<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ly equivocal Kings, Kings in name, but in reality Subjects, and have the People for their ſovereign Lord, who in theſe unhappy governments, as <hi>Themiſtocles</hi> calls them in his Epiſtles, are indeed the Miniſters of God, and ought to be obey'd, not onely for wrath, but alſo for Conſcience-ſake.</p>
            <p>But the opinion that I am ſpeaking againſt is this, that the People are the fountain and foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of all power and dominion, which is underſtood to be derived from them even upon thoſe whom Cuſtom calls ſovereign Princes, who are but their <hi>truſtees,</hi> or <hi>ſiduciary miniſters;</hi> with whom they have at leaſt a <hi>virtual</hi> contract, and if they do not perform their truſt by not uſing their power to the ends for which they received it, or abuſe it to contrary ends, then they forfeit the power and authority with which they were entruſted by them, and ought to be anſwerable for their defaults.</p>
            <p>I am confident this doctrine cannot be ſtrange to any man, that hath caſt his eyes never ſo little upon the ſeditious Pamphlets of theſe, or the late times. It is expreſſed, or implyed, taught, or inſinuated in moſt of them, which infect the unwary, the unthinking Vulgar with this Popiſh principle of Rebellion, before they are aware. I call it a Popiſh principle, becauſe the Papiſts, of all Chriſtians, firſt taught it, to arm the ſubjects at their pleaſure againſt their
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:61540:13"/>Sovereign, and by that means to revenge them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves upon the Princes that would not ſubmit un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the <hi>Pope.</hi> And indeed there never was any doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine better ſitted and invented to deſtroy Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chi<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, than this is: for as the unchriſtian opinion, that Epiſcopacy is an uſurpation over the Church, makes many people ſit ſo uneaſy and diſcontented under the Epiſcopal Juriſdiction, and hate Biſhops: So this unchriſtian doctrine, which makes ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereign and independent Princes Uſurpers over the peoples liberties, muſt alſo make all people that believe it, uneaſy and diſcontented under Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchical government, and ſecretly diſaffected to the Princes, in whoſe Realms they live.</p>
            <p>This we find by experience in this Kingdom, where this moſt unſcriptural and abſurd doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine is taught; unſcriptural I call it, becauſe it is ſo contrary to the Scriptures of the Old and New Teſtament, which aſſert ſuch wicked Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces as <hi>Tiberius, Nebuchadnezzar, Claudius</hi> and <hi>Nero,</hi> to be the miniſters of God, and commamds al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance both in ſubjection and non-reſiſtence unto them upon that account.</p>
            <p>And as it is moſt contrary to the Scriptures, and the whole ſtrain of primitive Chriſtian Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters; ſo is it in it ſelf chargeable with many ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurdities and difficulties, which the maintainers thereof cannot anſwer: For firſt, if the ſove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Power be radically and fundamentally ſeated in the people, then there is but one ſort
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:61540:14"/>of ſovereign government in the World, <hi>viz. Democracy,</hi> and by conſequence all other Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reigns, whether Senates or Princes, are Uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, and ought to be reduced, or depoſed. <hi>Secondly,</hi> They cannot tell us upon this hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſis, whether the ſupreme Power belongs to all the people promiſcuouſly, that have the uſe of reaſon, without any regard to Sex or condition, or onely to qualified perſons, to Men onely, and men of ſuch a condition and ſort. If men onely have a ſhare and intereſt in the ſupreme Power, by whoſe order and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, or by what Salique law of Nature were Women excluded from it, who are as uſefull members of the Commonwealth, and as neceſſary for humane ſocieties as the men are? Who gave the men authority to deprive them of their birthright, and ſet them aſide as unſit to med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle with Government; when Hiſtories teach us that they have weilded Sceptres, as well as Men, and Experience ſhews, that there is no natural difference between their underſtandings and ours, nor any defects in their knowledge of things, but what Education makes?</p>
            <p>But admitting that the ſovereign Power is onely in the Men, then they are as hard puzled to tell us, whether it b<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in all the men that have the uſe of reaſon promiſcuouſly, or onely in qualified perſons of ſuch an age, eſtate, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition. If all, then young and old, maſters
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:61540:14"/>and ſervants, fathers and children, poor and rich muſt have an equal ſhare and ſuffrage in the Government, which would make an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolerable confuſion; but if they ſay ſome, and once ſet limitations, then they can never tell by what order, or authority thoſe without the limits, which muſt be the more numerous part of the people, are ſhut out from the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment and from the concerns of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth, of which they are the greateſt part.</p>
            <p>But laſtly, let us ſuppoſe, as moſt of theſe Commonwealths-men do, that the Wife is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded with her Husband, the Child with the Parent, and the Servant with the Maſter, yet what proviſion is hereby made for all emancipated perſons, ſuch I mean, as have neither husbands, parents, nor maſters, muſt they come in for a ſhare of the Government, or not? or muſt onely maſters of Families have the whole management, and if they muſt, muſt the poor and rich, thoſe that have eſtates, and thoſe that have none, have an equal ſhare and intereſt in it, or if they muſt not, whence ariſes the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>equality, or who is it that hath authority to give ſome more power, and ſome leſs?</p>
            <p>Or if you will ſuppoſe a great Number of people not yet under any contract or regular aſſociation, who can have power to convene them together, to appoint times or places for
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:61540:15"/>meeting to preſide in their aſſemblies, to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine ariſing doubts, to draw up articles of agreement, form the ſcheme of the future Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, compute voices, and the like? and then in their aſſemblies, will the ſupreme Power reſt in the Major, or in the wiſer, or better part? and ſhall their acts conclude thoſe that could not, or would not come? When you have well conſidered all theſe difficult and p<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexed points, which attend this hypotheſis of placing all power in the People, you will eaſily perceive the excellency of the Scriptural hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſis above it. It is free from all the for<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned difficulties and abſurdities; it is more agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the original of Mankind from one ſingle created Father; it leaves not ſo many pretences for Sedition and Rebellion; it lays the higheſt obligations that can be upon the conſcience of the Sovereign to rule well: In a word, it is not onely the moſt religious, but the moſt rational, eaſie, and compleat account of Government, to ſay, that ſovereign States and Princes, are God's miniſters and not the peoples, that they derive their power from heaven, and not from men; and particularly, that they have the power of the Sword not by donation from the people, but by the ordinance of God.</p>
            <p>But in the <hi>third</hi> place, From this Apoſtolical doctrine about the power and authority of ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereign Princes, and States, you may perceive
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:61540:15"/>what a great ſin it is for the ſubjects of any government upon any pretence whatſoever, to take up Arms without authority from the law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Sovereign, be it in riots, tumults, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellions, or any other illegal meetings howſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever called; for God hath committed the power of the Sword to the lawfull Sovereign onely, and whoſoever takes it, and uſeth it without his authority, much more againſt it, uſurpeth the chief part of the ſupreme authority, and is left by our bleſſed Saviour to be puniſhed for his uſurpation by the Sovereign's Sword: <hi>Put up thy Sword again</hi> (ſaith he unto Saint <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> who drew it to defend his Maſter againſt the officers of the perſecuting Sanhedrim,) <hi>for all, that take the ſword, ſhall periſh by the ſword;</hi> and to this purpoſe, and almoſt in the ſame words, ſaith St. <hi>John,</hi> by way of precaution to the ſuffering Chriſtians: <hi>He that killeth with the ſword muſt be killed with the ſword, here is the faith and patience of the Saints.</hi> And accordingly the Apoſtle tells the Chriſtian ſubjects of that mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Nero,</hi> that the Powers that then were, were ordained of God, and that they, who reſiſted the Power, reſiſted the ordinance of God, and ſhould receive damnation, or condemnation to themſelves.</p>
            <p>To bear the Sword, or have the ſupreme diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of the Sword, is one of the <hi>jura majeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis,</hi> or eſſential rights of Sovereignty, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:61540:16"/>to the Sovereign by the <hi>Imperial laws</hi> of all governments, and by the ſame Imperial laws is it made capital to take it up againſt the Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign; and our Saviour, <hi>who came to deſtroy no man's civil rights, but to conſirm them,</hi> was in the firſt place tender of the Sovereign's rights, and of the Laws, by which they are eſtabliſhed, and confirmed them both: <hi>Render unto Caeſar</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>the things that are Caeſar</hi>'s, and one part of <hi>Caeſar</hi>'s prerogative, as a ſovereign Prince, and indeed the foundation of all the reſt, was to be accountable to no earthly power, nor liable to any coercion, or force: for were there any other power to which he was accountable, or which had a right to reſiſt him by violence or force of armour, that power would be <hi>Caeſar,</hi> or Sovereign, and not he.</p>
            <p>Wherefore had our Saviour given a power to Chriſtian ſubjects upon the account of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, or any other account whatſoever, to take up Arms againſt their Sovereign, he had ſet up one Sovereign, and one Sword againſt another, in every Government; and ſo had not come as he ſaid, <hi>to ſave mens lives, but to deſtroy them,</hi> and as he ſpoke in another ſenſe, <hi>not to ſend Peace upon the earth, but a Sword.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But inſtead of that, as I ſaid before, he hath confirmed the rights of Sovereignty, and the Imperial laws of every ſovereign government, which make it capital to reſiſt the Sovereign;
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:61540:16"/>and it is by theſe Laws, which I may call the firſt Table of every government, and by the Goſpel, which confirms them, that <hi>paſſive obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience,</hi> or <hi>non-reſiſtence</hi> becomes the double duty of Chriſtian ſubjects, who cannot take up the Sword againſt their Sovereign without reſiſting God, whoſe Miniſter he is, and making them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves juſtly liable to the ſtroak of that Sword, which God hath put in his hand.</p>
            <p>For God, to whom vengeance, or puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, belongeth, hath made him a revenger to execute wrath u<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>n his ſubjects that doe evil, but he hath not made <hi>them</hi> revengers to execute wrath upon <hi>him.</hi> Had he done ſo, he had ſet up two inſtead of one Sovereign in every Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment; but on the contrary, as his wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and honour obliged him, he hath reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved wicked Princes, and Tyrants for his own puniſhment, and hath allowed their ſubjects no Arms againſt them, but the Arms of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique and Apoſtolical Church, even the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive <hi>Artillery of prayers and tears.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Perhaps this may ſeem a very harſh doctrine to ſome inconſiderate people at firſt hearing, but if they well conſider that the reſiſtence of the Subjects brings greater evils, upon the publick, than the tyranny of the moſt wicked Sovereign, they will find, that the doctrine of <hi>paſſive obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience</hi> is founded in the higheſt reaſon, and that we are bound to praiſe the wiſedom and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:61540:17"/>neſs of God, who hath forbidden us a remedy, which is infinitely worſe than the diſeaſe. I need not ſend you far off to prove what I ſay, for in this little Iſland ſince the beginning of the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, there hath been perhaps as much Chriſtian bloud ſhed in <hi>pretended defenſive</hi> Wars, by the Anti-Epiſcopal Reformers, as in the firſt ten famous Perſecutions throughout the <hi>Roman</hi> Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire; and more men ſlain in the leaſt ſet battel of the late Rebellion, which was alſo called a <hi>Defenſive</hi> War, than by the tyranny of all the Kings of this Nation ſince the Crown was ſet upon the Conquerour's Head.</p>
            <p>But in the <hi>fourth</hi> place, To paſs over many other uſefull obſervations, as what a ſtrong obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion this doctrine lays upon the conſciences of all Chriſtian States, and Princes, and how unjuſtly the faithfull Miniſters of this Church are hated and aſperſed for preaching of it up, as if they deſigned to flatter their Prince into a Tyrant, and enſlave the People: I ſay, to paſs over theſe conſiderations, which would effectually vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate the Church and Clergy of <hi>England,</hi> and diſcover the malice of their factious enemies, we may ſee how much it is the ſpecial duty of all inferiour Magiſtrates whether Civil or Military, to take care that they employ not their power, which they have from their Sovereign againſt him, or doe any thing that may make his juſt Government uneaſie upon his ſhoulders; much
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:61540:17"/>leſs that may tend to the diſinheriſon of his Crown, the deſtruction of his Regality, or the diminution of his legal authority, and power.</p>
            <p>I make this obſervation, becauſe it hath been, and I am afraid ſtill is, a principle among our new Reformers, that the inferiour Magiſtrates have their power immediately from God, though they are choſen unto it by the Prince, and are God's Truſtees to ſee that he doeth his duty, and that if he will not, they may compell him, and reform without him, and raiſe forces to reſiſt his unjuſt force. But as this opinion is utterly againſt Scripture, the Hiſtories of all times, and the practice of all civil governments, wherein all <hi>inferiour</hi> Magiſtrates have their commiſſions from the <hi>Supreme:</hi> So is it utterly againſt rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, for then inſtead of one, we ſhould have many Sovereigns in every Government, Power againſt Power, and Sword againſt Sword; and if there be any man here ſo abſurd, that is not convinced of the danger and abſurdity of it at firſt hearing, I deſire him to admit this hypothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis but for one year into his own family: Let him ſuppoſe, that his Steward, or chief ſervant hath his Steward's authority immediately from God, and is God's Truſtee to ſee that he doth his duty, and that when he will not, he may force him, and reform his family without his conſent; but if he abhor this as an abſurd and impious pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſal, and as utterly inconſiſtent with the juſt
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:61540:18"/>exerciſe of the paternal authority in Families, it is every whit as bad in ſovereign States and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, and in a ſhort time would make the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme, the ſubordinate Magiſtrate's Slave.</p>
            <p>I have alſo made this obſervation, becauſe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny inferiour Powers and Magiſtrates have for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly, and I wiſh I could not ſay of late, done very much harm to the Crown, and given very ill example to the common people of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom by their undutifull and diſloyal actions. Were it needfull, I could prove this Charge by a volume of Examples out of the Hiſtories of the late times, to which I refer you; and heartily wiſh for the honour of God, and the Proteſtant Religion, that our preſent Sovereign, and God's Vicegerent, to whoſe goodneſs ſo many ungrate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full men owe their honours, and eſtates, and ſome incurable Traitours their honours and lives, had not of late been treated by ſome inferiour Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and Potentates more like a publick enemy, than a Prince.</p>
            <p>But in the <hi>fifth</hi> place, If God hath put the Sword in the Sovereign's hand, we may all learn how Neceſſary, and Honourable the profeſſion of a Souldier is, who beareth not the Sword in vain, but to fight the Lord's battels in defence of his Vicegerent, and to be a revenger to execute wrath upon them that doe evil. Every lawfull Souldier whether Common, or Commander is God's Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier, and what <hi>Jehoſaphat</hi> ſaid unto his Judges,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:61540:18"/>2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 19. may with a little alteration, be ſaid by the King to his <hi>Militia,</hi> or Army, <hi>Let the fear of Gob be upon you, and take heed what you doe, for the judgments which you execute are God's judgments, and you fight not for man but for the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have made this obſervation becauſe we have at leaſt one Sect among us, who ſay, that it is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull for a Chriſtian to bear Arms, and ſerve in the Wars under his lawfull Prince. But this is juſt ſuch another abſurd opinion, as that of the ſame men, who ſay it is unlawfull to take an Oath before the lawfull Magiſtrate, when we are requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to ſwear. I profeſs, I wonder what can be the ground of ſuch an abſurd opinion, and how the <hi>Socinians,</hi> who pretend to be Maſters of Reaſon, can teach ſuch an unreaſonable thing. It is a perfect contradiction to the doctrine of the Apoſtle, who here teacheth us, that the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereign beareth the Sword, as he is God's Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter, and that he beareth in not in vain, but to be a revenger to execute wrath upon him that docth evil; and if he bear the Sword by God's ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment, and for ſo great an end it muſt needs be lawfull, and laudable to bear it under him, juſt as becauſe he is the ſupreme Miniſter of Juſtice, ſome muſt needs ſerve under him in the adminiſtration and execution of Juſtice, and thoſe who doe ſo, are to be honoured in their ſeveral places upon the account of that civil au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, which they derive from him. The So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereign
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:61540:19"/>is the fountain both of Civil and Military authority, both are equally from God, and neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary for the ſupport of Government, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I confeſs, I cannot underſtand, why it ſhould be more unlawfull for a Chriſtian to buc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kle on the Sword at the command of his Prince, than to put on a Gown.</p>
            <p>But ſecondly, I have made this obſervation to let our ſeditious people ſee how little like Chriſtians they demean themſelves, in railing, as they have always done, at the <hi>King</hi>'s Guards, and of late at the loyal <hi>Militia</hi> of this City, calling them, as they did not many days ago, my Lord Mayor's <hi>Janizaries,</hi> my Lord Mayor's <hi>Army,</hi> and as they think very wittily, my Lord Mayor's <hi>Guards.</hi> Theſe people are themſelves an argument to prove, how neceſſary the Sword is for the quiet and welfare of Government, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the <hi>moto</hi> of your Shield, <hi>arma pacis fulcra,</hi> that <hi>arms are the cauſe of peace.</hi> They ſhew us what we muſt expect from them were it not for the Sword; and God be praiſed, that both the King, and the Lord Mayor have their Guards to defend them, otherwiſe, I fear, the ſpirit of <hi>Corah,</hi> which reigns ſtill in theſe men, would ſoon puſh them on to pull his Lordſhip out of his Chair, and His Majeſty out of the Throne.</p>
            <p>But in the laſt place, if God hath put the Sword into the Sovereign's hand, and the <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litary,</hi> as well, as the <hi>Civil</hi> Power be derived
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:61540:19"/>from him, you may ſee how Honourable a Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence the Science of Arms is, and how uſeful, and Profitable to all Governments Schools of Arms are, wherein Men diſpoſed for Martial Employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments may learn the Military Diſcipline, and how to be Expert <hi>in feats of Arms.</hi> Such Honourable Societies are His Majeſties Nurſeries for the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litia, as the Inns of Court are for the Law, and the two Univerſities for the Church; and as it is to be wiſhed, and endeavoured, that no Perſon be bred in either of the former, who would em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy their Tongues, and Pens againſt Gods Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant and their Soveraign: So is it to be wiſhed, and all poſſible Endeavours ought to be uſed by you, who are Members of this Honourable Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, that none be admitted into it, at leaſt into the Government of it, who will likely ſo miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>employ their Swords.</p>
            <p>You are the <hi>Chef d'ordre,</hi> the Chief Academy of this kind in His Majeſties Dominions; and as you are the moſt Illuſtrious for the Number, and Quality of your Members, ſo may you ever be the moſt Exemplary for Chriſtian Loyalty; and imitable Patterns for all His Majeſties Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of that Faith, and Allegiance, which is due unto him by the Law of <note n="†" place="margin">Cokes Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vin'<hi>s Caſe.</hi>
               </note> Nature, as well as the Municipal Laws of this Land.</p>
            <p>May you all (according to the Ancient Oath of Allegiance wont to be Adminiſtred in Courts of<note n="*" place="margin">Britton. c. 29.</note> Leet) <hi>Be Faithful and Loyal to our Sovereign
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:61540:20"/>Lord the King, and his Heirs, and bear them Faith and Fealty of Life, Limb, and terrene Honour, and never do them hurt, or damage, but Defend them to your Power.</hi> But if notwithſtanding your Care, and Endeavours to the contrary, any diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>affected Perſons have, or may hereafter creep in among you, let their Right-hands forget their Cunning, and ceaſe to be dextrous in handling the Sword.</p>
            <p>Let them never be able to ſtretch forth Hand or Sword againſt the Lords Anointed; or if they do, let them proſper according to the preſage of our Bleſſed, and Obedient Saviour, who ſaid, <hi>He that taketh up the Sword</hi> (that is without, or againſt Autority) <hi>ſhall periſh by the Sword. Let their Calamity,</hi> as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>riſe ſuddenly: Let ſwift Deſtruction,</hi> as <hi>David</hi> pray'd againſt his Enemies, <hi>come upon them unawares; let them be as the Chaff before the Wind, and the Angel of the Lord ſcattering them:</hi> Let all this come upon them as upon <hi>Abſalom, Brutus, Caſſius,</hi> and <hi>Choerea;</hi> and I hope there is none ſo diſloyal in this Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, at leaſt in this Honourable Company, that will not heartily ſay <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There are other Excellent Uſes to be made of this Doctrine, eſpecially againſt the unchriſtian Practiſes of thoſe Men, who not having the fe<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r of the King of Kings before their Eyes, love to ſpeak and do every thing, as far as ſafely they may againſt the Honour of his Vice-gerent;
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:61540:20"/>ſtandring his Perſon and Government, belying or miſ-conſtruing his beſt Proceedings, blaming, or Cenſuring his moſt Innocent Actions, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighting in his Misfortunes, Triumphing in his Wants, Aggravating his Infirmities, diſperſing Stories and Rumours to his Prejudice, and lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving to do every thing that tends to weaken his Autority, and withdraw the Hearts of his People from him, and render him Odious, and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible in their Eyes.</p>
            <p>If you ask theſe Men with what Conſcience they can thus treat their Soveraign, they will tell you, they do nothing but what they can Juſtifie by <hi>Law;</hi> as if the Laws of the Land, and not the Laws of the Goſpel were the compleat, and adequate Rule of Chriſtian Duty, Subjection, and Obedience: Or, as if Men were to be Try'd at the laſt Judgment by thoſe, and not by theſe.</p>
            <p>But alas, the Man of God, as the Apoſtle calls a Chriſtian, cannot be made Perfect in any one Duty by the Laws, nor furniſhed by them unto every good Work, but quite contrary, the Laws of the Realm will allow us to do many grievous things againſt Father, Mother, Wife, Children, or any other ſort of Relations, or Neighbours, for which, without Repentance, we ſhall be ſurely Damned. Wherefore as the Laws of the Land are not the Meaſure of our Duty of our Parents, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſo neither are they the Perfect Rule of our Duty to our Prince, as it is plain from
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:61540:21"/>the Verſe after my Text, where the Apoſtle having told the <hi>Romans,</hi> that the Emperour was the Miniſter of God, he then adds, <hi>Wherefore you muſt needs be ſubject, not only for Wrath,</hi> or fear of Legal Puniſhment, <hi>but alſo for Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience-ſake.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To Conclude all; theſe Diſloyal Men, with which theſe Kingdoms ſo abound, Act more like <hi>Greeks</hi> than Chriſtians, and as if they had been bred at <hi>Athens,</hi> and <hi>Sparta,</hi> rather than in the School of Chriſt: Otherwiſe they would be better Affected towards Gods Anointed; they would Pray more for him, and Murmure, and Clamour leſs againſt him, as knowing, that God giveth us what Kings ſoever he pleaſeth, and that the Kings Heart is in the Hand of the Lord, and that he turneth it whitherſoever he will. He is King of Kings, Lord of Lords, and the only Ruler of Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. He is the Fountain of Soveraign Power, every King is his Vice-gerent, and every Kingdom a Theocracy, and therefore let us bleſs the Lord before all the Congregation, and ſay, in the words of <hi>David,</hi> 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 29. <hi>Thine, O Lord, is the Greatneſs, and the Power, and the Glory, and the Victory, and the Majeſty: For all that is in the Heaven, and in the Earth is thine; thine is the Kingdom, O Lord, and thou art exalted, as Head above all.</hi> Which in other words is the very Doctrine of the Apoſtle, who ſaith, That <hi>there is no Power, but of God, and that he beareth not the Sword in vain, becauſe he is the Miniſter of God,</hi> To whom, Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt, be aſcribed, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>AMEN.</closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:61540:21"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
